Soviet Union Reformed Church Subject Files, Inclusive: 1971-1989, undated, Bulk: 1986-1989.
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Soviet Union Reformed Church Subject Files
Inclusive: 1971-1989, undated, Bulk: 1986-1989.
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
43
Keston Institute, 1969 -
10 folders
The Soviet Union Reformed Church Subject Files contain materials related to the Reformed Church in Ukraine, Hungary, and the Transcarpathian region with a special focus on statistics and numbers of the churches.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the named changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston College collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist countries. The Keston Archive and Library housed numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
The Keston Center received files related to the Reformed Church in the Soviet Union from 1971-1989. The majority of the documents discuss the Reformed Church specifically within Ukraine with a few references to the Reformed Church in Hungary.
The Reformed Church developed out of the 1517 Reformation but later became more closely associated with the teachings of John Calvin and Presbyterianism. Similarly, Calvinism flourished during the1500s in Ukraine. Between the mid-1600s and mid-1800s, external factors diminished the Ukrainian Reformed Church. After this period, the Reformed Church united with the Baptist Church for general support as well as protection from the government. Nonetheless, the Reformed Church experienced persecution under the Soviet regime.
Scope and Content
The Soviet Union Reformed Church Subject Files contain articles, cross references, clippings, abstracts, publications, and a bibliography from 1971 to 1989 with the bulk spanning from 1986 to 1989. The majority of the materials focus on Ukraine, Hungary, and Transcarpathia. Many documents reference the sizes and number of churches, pastors, clergy, and members. Additional common terms and ideas in the documents are Karpato-Ukraine, Calvinists, persecution, and theological training in Budapest.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received the Soviet Union Reformed Church documents in one folder. Each document has been organized based on its subject designation and date.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 43.
Related Resources
Related references
"Reformed church." Encyclopedia Britannica, August 15, 2021. Accessed December 10, 2021.
“Our History.” Christian Reformed Church. Accessed December 6, 2021.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Keston College -- Archives.; Keston Institute -- Archives.
Places
Soviet Union -- Religion.
Subjects
Reformed Church -- Hungary.; Reformed Church -- Ukraine.
Genres
Articles.; Publications.
- General, 1971-1989, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  Articles and publications about the Reformed Church in the Soviet Union with specific focus on Ukraine and additional references to Hungary.
  Acquisition Information
  Accession No. 43.
  - Reformed Church. General, 1971-1974, 1977, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - List of Reformed Churches, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Reopening (opening) of (new) Reformed churches; reconsecration (consecration), 1989 February (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Reformed Church Life, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Reformed Church. Clergy, Priesthood, 1987 December (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Reformed Church Pastoral Statistics, 1986 November (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Reformed Church. Visits from foreign delegations (1989), 1989 May (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Reformed Church. Theological Education, 1988 January-February (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Reformed Church. Statistics, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Reformed Church. Relations with Fellow Believers, 1989 July (Box 1, Folder 10)